Preliminary Guide to the Stanley Russell McCandless Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stanley Russell McCandless papers
1920-1985
MS 1415
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
The papers include correspondence, scripts, glass slides, and other papers documenting the career of Stanley McCandless.
McCandless, Stanley R. (Stanley Russell), 1897-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Glass teaching slides (4 linear ft.) were transferred 1991 Feb from Accession 1986-A-026, Drama School Records, YRG 22-A. Gift of Stanley R. McCandless, Jr., 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Grade books in box 11 of Accession 1986-M-034 is restricted until January 1, 2065 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Biographical / Historical
Stanley Russell McCandless was born in 1897. He was educated first at the University of Wisconsin and then received a master's degree in architecture from Harvard University in 1923. The following year, he joined the architectural firm of McKim, Mead, and White, but ventured to Yale University's drama department the following year. In 1926, McCandless began teaching courses in stage lighting. He stayed at Yale until 1964, when he retired as professor emeritus. Over the course of his career, McCandless helped light numerous stages at Yale and other universities and was a lighting consultant for the United Nations Assembly Hall, Radio City, the National Gallery, and the Trans World Airlines terminal at John F. Kennedy Airport. He died in 1967, aged 70.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, scripts, glass slides, and other papers documenting the career of Stanley McCandless.
Arrangement
Arranged by record type.
Drama; McCandless, Stanley R. (Stanley Russell), 1897-; Yale University -- Faculty
- Original accession
  - Glass teaching slides (Box 1–4)
- Additional Material, 1920-1970; Accession 1986-M-034
  - Syllabi, writings, bibliography (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1967 (Box 2)
  - Lighting research files (Box 3)
  - Project files, 1925-1967 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, lighting research files (Box 5)
  - Postcards, printed materials, manuscript (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Drawings (Box 8–10)
    - Oversize (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Gradebooks, circa 1928-1964 (Box 11)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted until January 1, 2065 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
- Additional Material, 1923-1985; Accession 2005-M-048
  - Biographical materials, 1923-1985 (Box 1)
  - Testimonial correspondence, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Syllabus of Stage Lighting, 1937, 1949, 1958, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Illuminating Engineering Society award medal, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Oversize materials
    - Photographs of sets, undated (Box 4)
    - Paintings, 1928 May 28, undated (Box 4)
    - Illuminating Engineering Society award, 1982 August 9 (Box 4)